[music]
>> You may think our modern world was born
yesterday,
but it wasn't. Not even the day before
yesterday.
Democracy in the streets and the rise of
people power,
the raw passion of national belonging,
good and bad.
Our obsession with the self,
with our own psychology, and the dark
recesses of the human mind.
Even our love of nature,
and our concern for the future of the
planet.
All of this
was the creation of the Romantics,
a generation [music] of artists living
and working 200 years ago, around the
time of the French Revolution.
Their art was created over nearly a
century of upheaval and change,
and it speaks to us now with as much
ferocious power as it did then.
>> [music]
>> I mean, they should have been our
leaders, really. You know, they should
have been our political leaders.
I might as well know we live [music] in
one of the richest countries on Earth,
but kids are being exploited just down
the street.
The Romantics lived hard, worked
feverishly, and many of them died young.
But we still think with their mind, we
feel with their emotional heartbeats, we
see with their eyes and we listen with
their ears. As surely as if we saw them
walking down the street, they are still
with [music] us, right here,
right now.
>> [music]
>> It gets you every time, doesn't it?
Wherever you happen to be, the songs of
our homeland.
This one set to words written by the
romantic poet William Blake.
>> [music]
>> There've been allegiance to monarchs and
rulers before,
but it was the romantics who gave us
this intense passion for the nation.
Who in their poetry, music and art
transformed the sentimental fondness we
all feel for our place of birth into
something bigger and deeper.
The secular devotion of national
belonging.
>> [music]
>> But that same passion flowing through
almost a century of revolution and war
also produced something much darker,
an angry twin.
The hater of foreigners, the divider of
us and them.
>> [cheering]
>> We are going to build the wall.
>> And that tribal fury is very much with
us today.
But where did this feverish passion for
homeland begin?
Well, for many romantics, it began here
in Switzerland,
with a diagnosis of something innocently
human.
Nostalgia.
Nationalism is above all the emotion of
longing to go back or stay where you
came from. And if you came from here,
spectacular Swiss Alpine mountain
village, of course you would feel
essentially nostalgic for your
birthplace.
It was a Swiss doctor, Dr. Johannes
Hofer, at the end of the 17th century,
who published a learned thesis which
treated nostalgia as a clinical medical
condition.
The term itself came from the Greek
nostos, the deep desire to return to
your native country, and algia, acute
pain and suffering.
Now, Hofer had actually seen that the
Swiss were particularly susceptible to
this. Swiss soldiers serving abroad,
serving the king of France, for example,
could be rendered unfit for military
service by this deep, powerful wish to
go back home.
And it was serious. It could rob you of
your appetite. You would shrink to
absolutely nothing. It could rob you of
your sleep. And Johannes Hofer, at any
rate, thought that in some extreme
circumstances,
nostalgia
could actually kill you.
To ward off this lethal malady, Hofer
suggested keeping patients away from
anything that reminded them too much of
home, food, folk stories, and especially
music.
>> [music]
>> In particular, for the Swiss, the sound
of the kuhreihen.
>> [music]
>> These were simple melodies played on
Alpine horns that echoed around the
landscape summoning the cattle back to
their home in the valley pastures.
The history of nationalism is strikingly
a musical story.
It's poetry, it's lyrics. And that's
what I think actually makes it an
authentically popular culture and indeed
still does. You don't have to be
scholarly or learned and the 18th
century you didn't even have to be
literate feel its raw emotional power.
Because the feeling for fatherland above
all came at you singing.
And what it sung was what you might have
heard from your father and mother
snatches of melody, local folk dances,
ballads, nursery rhyme.
Country feeling always spoke with a
sense of your own particular distinctive
culture. It sang with the voice of your
own ancestry.
More often than not, the long [music]
road to nationalism starts with a sense
of loss.
For the romantics, [music] it almost
always began with the overwhelming
humiliation of defeat.
Nowhere was this more true than in 18th
century Scotland.
In 1707,
after centuries of war, Scotland finally
lost its independence in the union with
England.
And it was a fear that authentic
Scottish culture might dwindle away or
even disappear.
It was an article of romantic faith that
art could keep the love of homeland
alive.
That was certainly what a young Scottish
poet, Robert Burns, felt acutely.
Growing up in the 1770s in Southwest
Scotland, Burns knew the union couldn't
be undone.
But what he could do was to create
authentically Scottish poetry and a
songbook that could hold its own against
the oncoming tide of English culture.
And in his brilliant hands, it worked
like a dream.
>> [singing]
[music]
[singing]
>> Scottish singer-songwriter Eddi Reader
made a name in the '80s with her band
Fairground Attraction.
And it was Burns' irresistible
magnetism,
much of which he put on show in this pub
in the village of Mauchline, that she
credits for pulling her back to the
music and poetry of her own country.
>> [singing]
[singing and music]
>> Everyone's a bit obsessed with Burns.
[music] They're all a bit in love with
him, and they all have a bit of him in
in them.
Five minutes.
I had a hit with Perfect when I was 28.
[music]
And I went to France and then went to
London. I thought I'd use traditional
Scottish music as a kind of [music]
a little bridge for me to get home.
I started collecting ones I remembered
and then it just happened to be that
they were all Robert Burns songs. I
didn't realize.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> And when you said you know it was a
bridge of taking you home, home is the
language really as well, isn't it? He
spoke in his own language and he didn't
even actually know that he was a good
poet or a bad poet. He just did it.
>> He wanted to give what he heard in the
pub and what he heard in the street and
what he heard in Scotland. You know,
mainly in the Scottish dialect.
>> Cuz the people are material and you
know, Bob Dylan uses people as material.
So did Johnny Rotten. It's just kind of
us. We are material. The people that he
uses words. Like you would meet them
driving taxis or just a guy, a plumber
that I met came up to me and he went
"I love your Burns stuff." he says. "My
favorite one is you see young Jackie
Co-da-Lord what struts and preens and
all that."
He's but a coof for all that, for all
that, for all that. The way he said it
to me
I just got it.
Burns knew how the people talked and
sang because he was one of them.
Born into a tenant farming family in
Ayrshire,
after his father's death in 1784,
Robert, then in his early 20s, [music]
took on this farm called Mossgiel along
with his brothers. [music]
Struggling to make a living, it was here
in between mucking out the cows and
threshing the wheat that Robert first
turned his hand to writing [music] a
completely new kind of poetry.
One rooted in the experiences of
ordinary Scottish life.
When you think of every kind of poet in
the romantic [music] movement, you know,
who hymns the beauties of nature, but
none of them actually has to do the
bloody hard lifting. And he has to do
his share of plowing and threshing and
all the really hard stuff that goes with
a farm like this.
He describes this farm as sodden and
difficult. And you think about the day
of Robert Burns in a place like this.
And everybody knows that when Robert is
doing this very hard work, he's dreaming
poetry. At least he must do at the end
of the day in the barn.
And what he does, and only he does, you
can't think of anyone in Britain,
really,
feeds his daily grind, his daily
experience both of pain and joy
into the words on the page like Burns.
To start with, he wrote his poems to
show off in the village and down the
pub.
But soon they turned into something much
bigger.
Taking what seemed to be the simplest
subjects, mice, haggis, cottage suppers,
their power owed everything to be
written not in the conventions of
English poetry,
but in a Scottish dialect, in the
rhythms and speech [music] of ordinary
working people.
In one poem, Burns turned his own
experience of disturbing a mouse's
[music] nest with his plow into a hymn
of kinship between a lowly field mouse
and a hard-pressed tenant farmer tilling
Scotland's soil.
Wee, [music] sleekit, cow'rin, tim'rous
beastie,
O what a panic's in thy breastie!
Thou need na startle awa sae hasty, wi'
bickering brattle!
I'm truly sorry man's dominion has
broken nature's social union, and
justifies [music]
that ill opinion which makes thee
startle at me,
my poor, earth-born companion,
and fellow mortal!
But, Mousie,
thou art no thy lane,
in proving foresight may be vain:
The best laid schemes o' mice an' men
gang aft agley,
An' lea'e us nought but grief an' pain,
For promised joy!
>> [music]
>> But once playful and profound,
no one had heard anything like these
poems before.
When they were published in 1786,
everyone, townsmen and country folk
alike, loved what he'd done.
>> [music]
>> Overnight, the plowman poet became a
star, Scotland's national bard.
In 1787,
followed by adoring fans,
Burns toured his country on a series of
celebrity book tours.
But he also had an added purpose to
rescue and collect traditional Scottish
songs and ballads for an anthology
called The Scots Musical [music] Museum.
He wanted, he said, to make a pilgrimage
through Caledonia,
to visit its castles and battlefields,
[music] what he called the abodes of its
heroes.
Riding into the northeast heartland of
his own family's Jacobite history,
Burns's journey turned [music] into a
kind of communion with his country's
heroic and tragic past.
But Scotland's historic monuments
weren't just an outdoor museum, they
also spoke to its present troubles in
revolutionary times.
In 1792,
fired up by the French Revolution, riots
and protests broke out on the King's
birthday in Edinburgh and continued in
towns and villages across Scotland
demanding liberty and political reform.
Terrified that the [music] fires of
Republican Revolution have been lit in
Scotland. In 1793, the British
government arrested and tried a group of
Scottish radicals,
later sentencing two of them [music] to
death and the rest with transportation
to Australia.
Burns's politics had always been
complicated, but he was an instinctive
Republican, and these events sharpened
his feelings about the Union, leading
him to write his most politically
charged song.
Well, this is something that's
incredibly precious. The manuscript of
one of Burns's most famous, if not the
most famous poems, Scots Wha Hae. It's
known all over Scotland, and it's a
document of uncompromising political
radicalism.
And this was written at a moment of
intense political crisis, not just for
Scotland, but for the whole of the
British state. And ostensibly,
it's the address that Robert the Bruce
gave to his troops before Bannockburn.
But actually, it's about a lot more.
>> [music]
>> Setting it to the marching tune played
by Scottish troops during what was
Scotland's most famous victory against
the English in 1314,
Burns turned Robert the Bruce's words
into an enduring anthem of Scottish
defiance.
And so, it begins as a romantic
historical piece.
Now's the day, and now's the hour. See
the front of battle lour, or see
approach proud Edward's power, chains
and slavery, and so on. But the end
builds into something [music] which is
as close as Burns gets to spitting in
the eye of the [music] English state.
He says explicitly that this is not just
about history. It's about Scottish
liberty.
The last stanza could have come out of
the mouth of
>> [music]
>> any French revolutionary. It's the kind
of Scottish Marseillaise.
Lay [music] the proud usurpers low.
Tyrants fall, and every foe.
Liberty's in every blow. Let us do or
die. This is the anthem
of Scottish freedom.
Scots, wha hae wi' Wallace bled,
[singing]
Scots, wham Bruce has aften led, welcome
to
your gory bed, or to victory.
Now is the day [singing]
and now is the hour.
See the front of battle [singing]
line.
See approach proud Edward's [singing]
power. Chains and slavery.
Wha will be a traitor's knave? Wha can
fell a coward's [singing] grave? The
song has long become Scotland's
unofficial national anthem. Wha for
[singing] Scotland's
king can fill a traitor's
grave?
Wha will be a traitor's knave?
Burns was convinced that music could
trigger a great swell of fellow feeling,
even if you were separated by wealth,
rank, or education.
Free man stand [singing]
and free man fall. Let him follow
me.
Everyone could sing their way to
national togetherness.
Those in chains and in slavery. By our
sons and servile chains. But above all,
it's his uncanny ability to give voice
to the great chorus of the Scottish
people
that explains why he still stirs such
passion.
Lay the proud usurper
low.
Tyrants [singing] fall on every foe.
Liberty's
in every blow.
Let us do
or die.
Wha! WOO! WOO!
>> [cheering]
>> WOO!
WOO!
>> FROM SIBSCO, Skelmorlie to Aberdeen,
northern Britain. That's right. That's
exactly where Skelmorlie is. But Burns
saved every song, every poem, every
word, and made us Scotland again.
In the decades following the French
Revolution, Scotland wasn't the only
country brooding on the loss of culture
and tradition at a time of national
crisis.
The same thing was happening in the
middle of Europe, in the German lands.
In the early 1800s, Germany was not a
unified nation, but a crazy quilt of
small states, bishoprics, and kingdoms.
They were united by language, but
divided by everything else. And one by
one, they fell like ninepins to the
invading French, led by Napoleon
Bonaparte.
Child of the Enlightenment, Napoleon
liked to claim he was bringing French
modernity, a new empire of reason,
sensible uniformity of institutions and
codes of [music] law.
All of which was poison to the romantic
mind.
Licking the wounds of their military
humiliation,
German writers and artists asked
themselves how they had fallen so low,
and what needed to be done.
So, driven by a mounting sense of
nationhood, they ventured deep into the
woods and forests of the German
landscape in search of their ancestral
past.
This is where in a world of Frenchified
sameness, they hope to rediscover the
roots of their own native culture, what
they called Deutschtum, German-ness.
And to do that, they look back to the
work of one of their most revered
philosophers.
The inventor of what it means to belong
to what you might call a cultural tribe
was an 18th century German philosopher,
Johann Gottfried Herder.
In a number of essays and books and
articles, Herder challenged a
fundamental principle of the
Enlightenment, namely that once we're
all liberated from old wives' tale
superstitions, including religious
superstitions, folklore, ballads, we
were free to become rational creatures.
And once we are rational creatures, we
were all the same wherever we lived.
Herder said, "No, actually we aren't.
We're the products of
innumerable ancestral deposits of
memory, custom, dress, and especially
song and folk poetry."
And he thought there was nothing to be
ashamed of about that.
Yes, Herder invented the idea of
German-ness, but he didn't necessarily
think it was superior to Icelandic-ness
or something else. He was just against
the flattening of difference. For him,
difference, whether you liked it or not,
was a deep truth about human nature.
Much of what Herder had to say
was a response to the anxieties of
becoming modern,
of the rush into money, materialism,
[music]
and metropolitan uniformity.
Wouldn't he and the Romantics believed
is that what we all needed to live truly
human lives was a sense of belonging, a
connection to the traditions of our own
tribe.
And you know, I think he actually put
his finger on something incredibly
important, not just for his own time,
but for our own time, too.
That the more modern we become, the more
we need anchorage.
Anchorage in memory, in dreams, in
ancestry, in myth, in the whole universe
of our connected imagination.
In the early 1800s, Herder's ideas had a
profound effect on the whole generation
of artists, not least the young painter
Caspar David Friedrich.
The son of a candlestick maker,
Friedrich grew up in the small town of
Greifswald, near the woods and cliffs of
Rügen Island, on the North German coast.
>> [music]
>> Precociously talented, he left home to
train as an artist in Copenhagen, then
moving to Dresden to start his career.
It was while he was there, in 1807,
that Napoleon's troops marched into his
hometown.
In the archives of the local museum,
there's evidence of just how intensely
Friedrich felt about the humiliation of
French occupation.
So, this is a letter written to his
younger brother, who has gone to Lyon in
France in order to pursue work as a
carpenter.
And it's written in this beautiful late
18th century hand. Leon is written very
hard with a quill in in large capital
letters. And what he's saying to his
brother is that "Du fühlst es selbst,
dass es nicht recht ist." You yourself
know that it's a wrong thing.
"Dass du als Teutscher in Frankreich
bist." That you a German are in France.
And he goes on to say that the only
thing that consoles me about that is
that you yourself do indeed know this.
Otherwise, I would doubt your
Teutschheit, your Germanness.
And then he says something even more
extraordinary, which is a very tough
thing for an older brother to say. He
says, "As long as you're in France, I
must ask you not to write to me again."
So, if you want any sort of sense that
Friedrich has really incredibly invested
in a patriotic sensibility about what it
means to be German in a difficult time
of defeat and humiliation, this letter
really says it all.
For Friedrich, that question what it
meant to be German was reinforced by an
even more personal loss.
For in 1809,
Friedrich's father, his only surviving
parent, died.
Returning home for the first time under
French occupation,
Friedrich made a pilgrimage to the
places that reminded him of his family's
past.
The search for his father and his
fatherland became one.
At the town where his father was born,
he sketched the ancient oaks that stood
guard over the fields.
And further down the coast, he drew the
ruins of Eldena Abbey, where he and his
father used to walk [music] when he was
a boy.
For Friedrich, these Gothic ruins
represented the spirituality and
strength of Germany's once great
medieval [music] Christian past.
On his return to Dresden, Friedrich
brought all his experiences and emotions
together in one of his most spellbinding
and eerie paintings, The Abbey in the
Oakwood.
This is a painting
most obviously about death, not least
the dying of light.
It's painted exactly at that special
moment between the final bits of the
sunset and the onset of evening.
At the heart of the painting, [music]
we have a shrouded group of mourners
carrying a coffin into the shattered
ruin of a Gothic church.
Everything is devastated and wrecked.
And above all, the most dramatic feature
of the painting itself are these trees.
These trees are in effect
anthropomorphized. [music]
They're people. This is a howling
lament, a funeral dirge.
Behind the trees, there is nothing.
There is just mist. It's just very, very
somber
philosophical reflection.
But but
>> [music]
>> there are all sorts of signs about a
change that may or may not happen. Not
least to that body.
The body in the coffin is being carried
into the church with a body of Christ
looking down. And of course, the death
of Christ is not a death.
It's a promise of a new life, the
promise of resurrection.
So, we have moments of resurrection
everywhere in [music] this painting.
Hanging in the sky
is a crescent moon,
a waxing moon. Day will follow the fall
of night.
Spring will follow winter. Friedrich has
even take the trouble
of actually putting tiny dots at the end
of those jagged twigs, the signs of the
buds of spring.
So, despite darkness descending,
there is hope of new life around the
corner, a hope of resurrection, not
least perhaps
with any luck
in the turn of history's wheel,
the resurrection of Friedrich's own
nation.
The resurrection of Germany.
The question was how that resurrection
was to happen.
Well, further south in another German
state invaded by French forces, two
young brothers thought they had the
answer. Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm.
In 1807,
Napoleon made their hometown of Castle
the capital of the new satellite kingdom
of Westphalia.
He installed his younger brother Jerome
on the throne.
And believing that the French language
was both more rational and more
civilized than German, made French the
official language of state.
But, the brothers Grimm knew how to
resist. As disciples of Herder, they
believed that it was by going back to
the language and folktales of the
people, the folk, that they would find
the roots of their own proud Germanic
culture.
Something they hoped would contribute
not just to a local, but to a national
reawakening.
In 1811, the brothers had an
extraordinary idea.
They wrote an appeal. Here it is in
front of me.
Asking for researchers to fan out across
the country and listen to regular people
telling stories, transcribe them, and
report back to fairytale command and
control here in Kassel. And the way they
put this appeal is very touching and
very emotionally powerful.
"Our fatherland," they said, "is still
filled with this wealth of material that
our honest ancestors planted for us, and
which despite the mockery and derision
heaped on it as just folktales,
continues to live unaware of its own
hidden beauty." In other words, what
seemed to be simple was powerful.
Whatever Napoleon could do, he couldn't
tear up the roots of that village folk
culture. And in a wonderful phrase,
Wilhelm Grimm said, "We could hear
faintly blowing the horns of Elfland."
The response to that call was
astonishing.
From all over the kingdom, ordinary folk
offered their stories, [music] and they
came from all walks of life.
From retired soldiers and fruit sellers
to pastors, cooks,
and servants in aristocratic households.
Published in 1812, the first edition of
what the Grimms called Children and
Household Tales,
the world they uncovered was far darker
than they'd ever imagined.
Well, these remind me of when I first
read the Grimm fairy tales. Maybe I was
six or seven and how absolutely scary
they seemed. The whole Hansel and Gretel
thing about freshly baked children.
But, I had no idea that what I was
reading was the softened, revised
version, made much more child-friendly.
The original version in 1812 was
spectacularly
fuller of cruelty and savagery.
Cannibalism, mutilation, death, incest.
They were horrifying.
Cinderella's ugly step-sisters, for
example, when they were trying on the
glass slipper, did not just have a tough
time trying on a slipper. They cut off
their toes to make it work.
The wicked queen in Snow White was not a
wicked stepmother. It [music] was her
actual mother. And what she asked the
woodsman to do was not just to abandon
her in the forest, but cut out her
heart, lungs, liver,
so they could be taken back to mommy,
who would then cook them and have them
for dinner.
>> [laughter]
>> Once upon a time, there was a stubborn
child who never did what his mother told
him to do.
The dear Lord therefore did not look
kindly on him and let him become sick.
No doctor could cure him and in a short
time he lay on his deathbed.
After he was lowered into his grave and
covered over with earth
one of his little arms suddenly emerged
and reached up into the air.
They pushed it back down and covered the
earth with fresh earth, but that did not
help.
The little arm kept popping [music] out.
So the child's mother had to go to the
grave herself
and smack the little arm with a switch.
After she'd done that
the arm withdrew
and then
for the first time
the child had peace beneath the earth.
The Brothers Grimm really knew what they
were doing. [music]
And it was not obviously meant for
children. It was meant for fully
grown-up townsmen, often middle-class,
who after a hard day's work could come
back and in effect so switch on a
particularly nasty video or TV. It was
actually fantasy horror entertainment.
They were trying to connect those
hard-working, tired townspeople with a
world the romantics kept on saying they
were in danger of losing the dark,
savage, German primeval [music] forest.
For the German romantics, [music] it was
in the forest, they were sure where
their nationhood was born.
A world away from modern civilization.
This was a more primitive world of magic
and violence, of ancient wisdom and
natural justice.
And it was here, two millennia before,
that the ancient German tribes had
defeated the Roman army and resisted
Roman occupation.
And so, it would prove once again.
>> [music]
>> In 1814, as the tide of war turned
against the French army,
Caspar David Friedrich painted this.
An image of a lone French cavalryman
facing massed ranks of German trees.
Is there anything more pathetic than a
cavalry officer who's lost his horse?
Not just lost his horse, this French
chasseur has also lost his regiment.
And he's lost the war.
Napoleon has been destroyed not so much
by history as by geography.
The snows of Russia and here, of course,
the great primeval forests of
Deutschland, of Germany.
There's nowhere to go in this particular
forest.
The chasseur we think must realize it's
a path in the woods in which you are
doomed to get lost. There's no way
forward and pretty much there's nowhere
back. And in case you didn't get the
message, there is a raven, the messenger
of death, perched on the broken stump of
the tree.
And the artist has done something
amazing with the composition. He wants
to make us feel [music] that the enemy
of that German woods, invincible, aren't
they? Aren't just in front of them,
they're behind them as well. And our
point of view is at the top of one of
those fir trees looking down on this
broken spectacle of imperial power.
Accept the inevitable. In the end,
Germany and its trees have won.
Nearly 60 years later, in 1871,
Germany finally became one nation.
But when the pendulum swung again, and
Germany lay defeated in the First World
War,
the power of romantic iconography proved
irresistible.
The Nazis perverted everything Halder
and Germany's liberal-minded romantics
had stood for.
And Friedrich's forest became not just a
symbol of German strength,
but of its ethnic purity.
The Holtzweg, the path through the
woods, can lead in two completely
different directions. One direction will
take you into a universe of magic, of
enchantment, of the kind of creative
flights of the imagination necessary to
establish an idea of a common
fatherland. In this case, a woodland
home.
But the other path can go to a very dark
place indeed, one of bloodshed and
brutality.
It took some time before German artists
could reenter the forests of German
history.
And when they did, [music]
like the painter Anselm Kiefer, they did
so as brutal demystifiers,
chopping down the trees and staining the
path with blood.
A generation on, they are still
obsessively entering the woods of
memory.
But now, with the more sympathetically
romantic [music]
eye.
Mariella Neudecker restages the
landscapes of Friedrich and the Grimms
in liquid-filled glass tanks that mimic
the atmospheric conditions of air,
light, and fog,
reconnecting us not just with the
darkness, but with the wonder and
mysticism of romantic art.
I guess what really drew [music] me to
romanticism was learning about the abuse
of the romantic imagery in the Third
Reich.
There's been a lot of issues in [music]
post-war Germany to sort of deal with
it.
I already feel like I'm one generation
down trying to take it on and [music]
deal with the politics that could be
embedded in something quite
harmless-looking.
To understand what it means to go back
to romantic imagery today.
You know, it has this sort of beautiful
side to it
and also a really dark underbelly.
I want people to have a sense of wonder
and then a sense of of fear and there's
sort of trigger. There's a sort of
mechanism where where people might sort
of conjure up memories of their
childhood or of stories that they've
read or anything like that and in some
way
that's really important to me.
I'm not sure if I'm sort of reclaiming
[music]
the landscapes but I think it's sort of
neutralizing somehow that political
weight on them.
And what I want is for people to
question [music] their perception and
question their understanding of those
images.
During the Third Reich, every German
knew just where the nation began deep in
the forest.
Where it would end though
was a different matter.
But further east for sure. It wasn't
September 1939
when Warsaw fell
alone with nothing to oppose the air and
land onslaughts but her small garrison
and the spirit of her people.
When Hitler invaded in 1939 [music]
the Polish nation became almost
overnight a conquered province of the
Third Reich.
In an act of brutal nationalist
aggression
over the next five years it would see
nearly six million of its citizens die
and many of its cities, most notably its
capital Warsaw, almost totally
destroyed.
Never giving up hope of liberation
the Polish resistance rallied around the
figures of their most famous romantic
artists.
In particular Poland's greatest composer
[music]
Frederic Chopin.
He had given his nation its heroic
soundtrack when his people were living
through the same experience a century
earlier.
When the heartbeat of Polish culture
wasn't even in Poland.
But here in Paris.
In the 1830s this was where Chopin
alongside Poland's most important
politicians, poets and artists had all
fled into exile after their beloved
homeland had not just been conquered but
completely [music]
wiped off the map.
With their memories of homeland
sharpened by separation, they created a
Poland of the imagination in their art.
In the 17th century Poland was huge. It
was an enormous chunk of territory but
territory isn't the point. It had its
own culture, its own language, its own
extraordinary idiosyncratic
institutions.
No other state suffered this
disappearing act. It was chopped up and
[music] consumed by the empires around
it, Austria, the kingdom of Prussia and
the Russian Empire.
In 150 years it goes from [music] being
this enormous, powerful, prosperous
territory
to have gone, vanished. So the issue
that that all raises what happens when
your country disappears? Does [snorts]
culture then matter more? Well, of
course. It comes to be all you have. So
the whole of the romantic [music]
fruitfulness of dreaming a Polish dream
in poetry, in novels, in history [music]
and especially in music happens as a
response to this traumatic disappearing
act.
For Chopin and his fellow exiles, it was
ultimately a cataclysmic event that had
caused their exodus and sealed their
fate as a people without a nation.
In November 1830, while Chopin was on a
concert tour in Vienna, Polish rebels in
his hometown [music] of Warsaw mounted a
doomed rebellion against Russian rule
that lasted for 9 months.
Facing the wrath of the Russian Tsar,
the Polish resistance finally collapsed
when in September 1831, the last rebels
retreated to the village of Wola where
they were slaughtered on the graves of
their ancestors.
Incoherent with grief, Chopin identified
the fate of his nation with that of his
family and poured out his anguish into
his diaries.
My poor father,
perhaps he's hungry.
Perhaps my sister [music] has fallen to
the wild Muscovite villainy.
My mother,
perhaps
a Muscovite has killed her, murdered.
And here I stand with empty hands.
I only express my pain from time to time
on the piano.
I despair.
But what good will that do?
The retributions were catastrophic.
Thousands of Poles were executed, lands
and homes were seized,
and Poland's name was erased from the
map.
After refusing a Russian [music]
passport, Chopin had no choice but to
join his fellow exiles in Paris,
never to set foot on his native [music]
soil again.
Expressing all his longing through the
piano.
Over the next 18 years,
Chopin dredged up memories of the folk
dances and mazurkas of his childhood,
transforming them into some of the most
heartbreaking romantic music ever
created.
>> [music]
[music]
>> In exile,
Chopin turned these humble melodies
>> [music]
>> into masterpieces of intense emotional
compression.
By turns wistful, haunted, even
defiantly [music] joyful.
Their intense nostalgia expresses the
painful longing to return home.
Chopin for Polish people, even people
who know nothing about music, love
Chopin.
You know, it's a symbol of Polishness.
It's It's an identity which they want to
preserve because there is no state
anymore.
The fact that he wrote
most of [music] his music abroad, and
most of it, you know, here in in France,
in Paris,
uh Uh,
there is this longing for something that
is lost.
>> Right.
I I How do you feel about the mazurkas?
I mean, how much do you feel they were
something that kind of organically came
out of
memory of homeland? Definitely comes
from
uh
folk idiom. But, especially towards the
later mazurkas, he really transcends all
of this and he goes uh
into crazy harmonies. But, you have
still, even in the late opus says, one
or two mazurkas suddenly incredibly
robust and primitive and and and and uh
like the
opus 56. [music]
>> [music]
>> And so on, yeah. You remember what
Schumann said, for example. Cannons
hidden in flowers, you know?
>> Yes. So, the flowers are always there.
The decoration is there.
The
the beautiful form is always there, but
inside is a volcano.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Poland finally regained its independence
in 1918.
But, under German occupation during the
Second World War, the Nazis set out to
eradicate the Polish nation and their
culture.
Chopin's music was banned. And after the
capture of Warsaw, his statue became the
first public monument to be destroyed.
And in 1944, as the Nazis brutally
crushed another doomed Polish revolt,
another battle was taking place in the
semi-destroyed Church of the Holy Cross.
A battle over Chopin's heart.
What could be a more perfect cult object
of sacred national devotion than the
heart of Frédéric Chopin? And here it
is, inside this enormous pillar of the
Church of the Holy Cross in Warsaw.
The battle this time is inside the head
of the German commander who gloried in
the name of General Erich von Bach. The
battle was between his obligation to
total military annihilation and
slaughter, and the other profound,
characteristically German instinct, his
absolute passion and love for music,
including that of Chopin.
And guess what? It was the latter which
actually won out amidst all the carnage.
The general secured the heart from
inside what was left of the pillar, gave
it to the Archbishop of Warsaw, and in
October 1945,
when the war was over, the heart was
brought back in an extraordinary public
ceremony and reinstalled where it is
now.
What actually triumphed, even in the
head of a Nazi commander, was the
ultimate, transcendent,
>> [music]
>> universal power and beauty of Chopin's
music.
>> [music]
>> The battle between national identity and
our shared humanity speaks to us as much
now as it ever did.
Years after the chaos and destruction of
the Second World War,
the roar of the angry tribe can once
again be heard in the streets,
even in Poland.
In a world convulsed by existential
crises, nationalism is perhaps our own
response to the fear that our identities
and traditions are once again under
threat in an increasingly bewildering
world.
As politics everywhere has become
dominated by nostalgia, the longing to
look back to some once-upon-a-time
rosy past,
culture has once again become a
battleground for competing visions of
what national belonging might mean.
When the romantics brought all the
trappings of national devotion into the
world, flags and anthems, songs and
stories, they were creating a community
of belonging every bit as powerful as
family or church.
But what they created is so viscerally
powerful
that it can also bring with it a
dangerous state of mind.
If the romantics' most enduring legacy
is the belief in the power of art to
connect us to deeper truths about who we
are.
Then its goal ultimately was not to
divide us,
but to remind us that in spite of all
our differences, every human heart is
the same.
One of the messages that the Romantics
left us with it's it's possible to
belong to the family of your own
country, its traditions, its stories,
its ballads, its music, its poetry, and
yet belong at the same time to humanity.
>> [cheering]
>> There's a wonderful line written by the
German poet Schiller in his Ode to Joy
that goes like this.
Be embraced, oh millions, with this
kiss, the whole wide world. That's what
the Romantics wanted. They wanted in the
face of everything that they had to deal
with that the ultimate message might yet
be
harmony.
>> [music]
[music]